I get easily hurt by other people.
(Questioner) Hello.
(Sunim) Hello.
I am a 27 years old PhD student
studying abroad.
I'm concerned about my timid
personality.
I get easily hurt and stressed out
by other people.
Last year, I taught math
to American college
students as a teaching assistant.
When students wouldn't listen or
leave in the middle of class,
I get really stressed out.
I'd like to learn how to reduce stress
from relationships with other people.
(Sunim) Do you think there are people
who intentionally give stress to others?
No, I don't think so.
(Sunim) Do you think there are people
who receive stress from others?
Yes, there are.
There's no one giving stress,
but there are many who receive it.
There aren't many who hurt
other people
but there are many who get hurt.
Would there be parents
who intentionally try to hurt their kids?
There aren't, and yet there are many kids
who are hurt by their parents.
Once I met and talked with
my elementary school friends.
A female friend claimed that
the boys used to bother her
by cutting off the girls' jump ropes.
She had a lot to complain about
from back in the days.
Many were stories of being hassled.
And yet among the male friends,
there was no one that remembered
doing such things.
They couldn't even remember
if such event happened.
From this we can observe,
that there aren't those who hurt others,
and yet there are many that are hurt.
Those who hurt others
don't remember their actions,
and yet the people
who were hurt remember them vividly.
They remember the details of
who did what, when and where,
even at the age of 60.
And yet the boy who bothered
her would say,
That can't be, when did I do that?!
Do you remember back in elementary school,
we used to get spanked
on our palms with a ruler
when we wouldn't do our homework?
You do, don't you?
And yet if you visit your teachers today
and ask if they remember spanking you,
would they remember?
Probably not, right?
Likewise, you all remember all the things
your husbands have done you wrong.
But if you ask him he'd say,
When did I ever do that?
The same applies to us all.
Your students would have left
in the middle of class
because they had a certain reason
to do so.
Some might have wanted
to go to the restroom.
Others might have not liked your teaching.
You have no clue why they had left.
And yet you think to yourself,
They must have not liked my class.
When I give lectures,
at times
a full audience sticks around
till the very end.
At other times, one third of the audience
from the back leaves during the lecture.
Maybe they were old and tired.
Maybe they had another appointment,
maybe they came as a group
and have to leave.
They'd have their own reasons,
wouldn't they?
Maybe they didn't like my lecture
all that much.
Whatever it is, they have
their own reasons for leaving.
And it doesn't have much to do
with my lecture.
Each have their own reason.
If I take it all personally, it wouldn't
be because I am self-conscious.
It'd be because I am
too proud of myself.
You think people should always listen to
what you have to say.
You think they should stay put
till the end of your lecture.
You think they should like your lecture.
To have such thoughts are incorrect.
You give lectures because it is
what you do.
Whether others like your lecture
or not is each to their own.
Yesterday I went somewhere
and gave a lecture.
A man in his 70s came up to me and
gave me a long criticism before leaving.
He said,
A monk should stick to
meditating.
You shouldn't be advising politicians.
He told me off for a while
and left without hearing
what I had to say.
As you see, everyone lives according to
their thoughts and beliefs.
You can't have control over everyone
and everything.
Little kids in school sometimes
fall asleep during class, don't they?
They do.
Didn't you all doze off during class
at times back then?
We all did.
You did a lot? (laughs)
Everyone has their own situation.
Hence to think,
How dare you doze off
during my lecture?
How dare you chat during my class?
To think as such is self-righteousness.
You're not understanding
what others are thinking.
You think you're the greatest
and you want proof from others,
hence the issue.
In reality, you're the only one
who thinks you're all that great.
Others think you're just as
any other person.
Do you think you're extraordinary?
No, it's not that...
You're just an ordinary person.
You're just the same as
any other weed on the sidewalk.
You should think of yourself
this way as you live your life.
People come and go.
That's their own concern, not yours.
If you're a Buddhist, you should pray,
Buddha, I am just the same
as a squirrel living the woods.
You should pray this way.
Does the squirrel ever complain
that rocks are too large or too small,
or that a tree is too high?
It doesn't, does it?
The squirrel simply lives
the way it was born.
In the same way,
how people react is each to their own.
It's their life.
You should live your life your own way.
I understand. Thank you.
Is it just this student that has
the problem, or is it us all?
We all are like her, are we not?
We care too much about
what others think.
Now sometimes there are people
who should be paying more attention
to others.
There are politicians who do
whatever they want
without taking others into consideration.
Those thick skinned people should care
what other people think.
But ordinary folks like us don't
intend to be mean
and hurt others, do we?
Our problem is that we try too hard
to be a nice person.
We want to be praised by others.
We want to be told we're nice,
we want compliments.
This is an attention deficit disorder.
We try too hard to be loved.
We shouldn't be like this.
Do rabbits in the woods want
to be loved by everyone
and seek attention from others?
They don't, do they?
They just live their own lives.
So should you.
Do you understand?
You should just live your life
as you want to.
Don't care what others have to say.
Don't be envious of a big house.
When I see a big house I think,
"Gosh, it must be so hard to keep
that house clean."
If the house is small, it's easy.
Even a lazy person can clean up
the house quite easily.
What's so great about a big house?
If you have too much food on the table,
you'll most likely overeat.
It's better to have just one
or two dishes at a time.
Eating less is better than
eating too much for your health.
Even if you smoke the best cigarettes,
it's still worse than not smoking at all.
Hence there's no need to envy those
that smoke the best cigarettes.
Putting on makeup isn't better than
wearing no makeup.
You don't agree on this one, do you?
I'm saying that if you want a simple,
natural life,
you won't be envying all these things.
Envying and wanting is in a way
a result of being brainwashed.
Do you understand?
I gave a lecture in Youngju yesterday.
A woman who attended my lecture
had sent me a letter.
She was suffering from depression,
so her mental state was rather fragile.
So I had advised her how to pray.
As there were too many people
at my lecture,
she handed me a letter instead.
A monk told me that my house has
a bad vibe.
Another monk told me that my house's
direction is bad.
Some other monk told me
something else was off,
hence I should buy an amulet,
I should do this, do that.
While she couldn't afford to
do all these things,
she didn't feel comfortable
ignoring their advices.
So she wrote to me saying,
Sunim, I have no money
so I'm sending you $20 in this envelope.
Please write me an amulet.
Honestly speaking, it's not right for
religious figures to do this.
Mentally fragile people can't just
brush off
what they heard. They can't.
If a monk tells someone, Your son's
in trouble, something's not good.
Fix your door, change this,
people inevitably cling onto that.
But if you practice just a bit,
you no longer have to
pay attention to such things.
Those people who say such things do so
to make a living.
Or they possibly may believe they really
have psychic powers.
Hence we don't need to reprimand them.
You just need to have a stance not to get
dragged around by others.
When the world is chaotic, we get
emotionally unstable.
When unstable, people take advantage of
our fragility.
Such things happen more and more.
Nowadays abortion is less common.
But most women in their 40s and 50s have
an abortion experience.
Buddhist temples used to take
advantage of the guilt of these women.
And tell them that they must pay for
special rituals to appease the spirits,
otherwise their children
will be in trouble.
Fragile people would fall prey to this.
There are those that threaten others
by saying
if you don't believe in Jesus,
you'd go to hell.
And then there are people on the streets
asking if they know 'the Way'.
They'd tell people to perform special
rituals for their every problem
and extort huge sums of money.
Things like this happen.
And yet we can't punish these things
by law.
Why not?
Because that's their own choices.
You may think
'Why not punish those fraudsters?'
But in a democratic society,
it's more important that you don't
fall for such frauds yourself.
Since there are so many of us
that are mentally
and emotionally fragile these days,
many fall as victims to these schemes.
When a society is in chaos people are
easily deceived by others.
When people's minds are not strong,
they become easily duped.
The reason we run these lectures is
because people care too much about
what others think.
You are easily swayed by what others say.
That's all because you are
not strong enough.
You're no better than a rabbit.
If you tell a rabbit,
Hey, if you go up there,
you'll get caught and die.
Does the rabbit care?
No. It keeps on going.
Even if it ends up dying, it goes.
You want shortcuts.
You want easy solutions.
You don't study,
but you want to go to a good university.
You want shortcuts like this.
Don't look for these easy solutions.
Remember, if you sow soybeans,
you reap soybeans.
If you sow red beans, you reap red beans.
You should be willing to face
the consequences of your choices.
You will be fine if you can live
your life with that motto.